All right, בוקר
טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ט"ז, Tes Zayin, 16, so
ט"ז, Tes Zayin, and we start at, what do we start? Oh
yes, top of ט"ז. Tes Zayin. We're even a line or two
ahead in שילה, נוב, וגבעון. Shilo, Nov, u'Givon.
So the question is where does the dirt for the that says
אשר יהיה
בקרקע המשכן, asher yihyeh be'karka ha-Mishkan, the dirt that will be on
the ground of the המשכן, Mishkan, so that means that it doesn't
have to actually dig it from there.
One opinion is you can bring the dirt in and pre-lay it,
although it is interesting that you don't lay it on the tile,
you lay it underneath the tile. But then there's another opinion, that's
what we see in this ברייתא braisa is איסי בן מנחם, Issi
ben Menachem, I believe it is. But then there's another opinion, where
was he?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we're going to get to that, but I just
wanted to remind us of the two opinions. That was איסי בן
יהודה, Issi ben Yehuda, no I'm sorry,
that was איסי בן מנחם, Issi ben Menachem, I was right.
First line of the דף. daf. And איסי בן יהודה Issi ben
Yehuda says, no, בקרקע המשכן, be’karka ha-Mishkan, actually you don't even have
to lay it on the ground. בקרקע המשכן be’karka ha-Mishkan somehow we
sort of bracket that, and what it's really coming to tell you
is that it not only applies in the המשכן, Mishkan, it even
applies to according to one version, שילה, נוב, וגבעון. Shilo, Nov, u'Givon.
רש"י Rashi crossed that out because a סוטה Sotah is sort of
like a יחיד yachid type of a קרבן, korban, but nevertheless תוספות
Tosafos says this is going according to the opinion that a יחיד
yachid קרבן korban could be brought at נוב Nov and גבעון Givon
where there was not the ארון Aron and it was really had
a status of a במה Bamah and other people and you could
bring on your individual במה, Bamah, it was not the single central
location. So that's a question whether you did it there. So that
includes that and it includes בית עולמים, Beis Olamim, it includes the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Now, in that discussion that it includes בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, just
to remind us what we said yesterday, one interesting thing I'll add
today, one interesting thing is that the גמרא Gemara sort of said,
well, like a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you know, טומאה Tumah applies
in the מקדש, Mikdash, normal טומאה, Tumah, טומאה קלה, Tumah kallah, like
a טומאת מת, tumas meis, all the more so should טומאה חמורה
Tumah chamurah of אשת איש eshes ish apply in the מקדש. Mikdash.
And that was a very strange question because on the one hand
it's not the same issue, it's not keeping the טומאה Tumah away,
it's doing a ritual relating to the טומאה. Tumah. But the other
thing that's very interesting is that it puts the two of them
in the same category. It is true that the תורה Torah uses
the phrase, you know,
ונסתרה והיא נטמאה, ve-nisterah ve-hi nitma'ah, she's been defiled, she's been made
טמאה, temeah, but we never have a הלכה halacha that it has
the
same... and it is true that the תורה Torah understands an idea
of טומאה Tumah as like
sin and corruption, moral sinful
defilement. אל תטמאו בכל אלה כי בכל אלה נטמאו הגוים, al titam'u
be-chol eleh ki be-chol eleh nitm'u ha-goyim, right? But at the same
time that's never
the same
טומאה. Tumah. If somebody is a sinner they can still go into
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? If somebody sinned with
עריות arayos and אשר נטמאתם בם asher nitmeitem bam or whatever, they
can still go into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so it is
interesting the way that it's sort of putting them in the same
category. And I want to just remind us though that this applies
elsewhere. For example, some of the basic הלכה halacha we have about
how to deal with a ספק safek in a case of טומאה,
Tumah, you know, you doubtly did you touch this object, not touch
this object, ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים טהור, safek tumah birshus harabim tahor,
ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד טמא, safek tumah birshus hayachid tamei, that's all
learned out from the סוטה Sotah when she goes into private in
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and she's assumed to be טמאה, temeah,
so we apply from a סוטה Sotah to this other type of,
you know, dead body type of טומאה. Tumah. And the other interesting
thing to remind us of is remember where it said where the
סוטה Sotah would stand. It said she would stand in שער ניקנור
Sha'ar Nicanor in the
מקום שמעמידין בו מצורעים ויולדות makom she-ma'amidin bo metzora'im ve-yolados where the
טמאים t'mei'im would stand, right? So how much are we trying to
conceptualize this also, right? That's another way of thinking about this. There
are like three ways of thinking about this ritual. One is like
the פשט pshat in the פסוקים, pesukim, which is to clarify if
she's innocent or guilty. The other is the emphasis of the משנה
Mishnah which is we're presuming she's guilty and it's to punish her.
And the third is, maybe it's a purification ritual, right? She brings
a קרבן, korban, she's טמאה, teme'ah, she does this weird thing at
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? So that's like another interesting... again,
it's very interesting this where we're bringing in the standard lens of
טומאה. Tumah. So that's one thing that came up yesterday at the
end that we sort of did very quickly at the end. And
the other thing I'll say and then we'll continue is why do
we need a פסוק pasuk to include the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
like isn't בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash always presumed to be included when
the תורה Torah says המשכן? Mishkan? So תוספות Tosafos has a whole
discussion and he has an interesting answer and he says maybe the
problem is it says בקרקע המשכן be’karka ha-Mishkan and the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash doesn't have קרקע, karka, the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash has
a floor. So maybe I would have thought that's why it wouldn't
have been פשט pshat included. Anyway that's what we have, a debate
whether you have to pre-lay it or can you do it straight
from just bring in the dirt and even take it straight out
of a basket. Okay, but nobody says that you have to dig
it.
Yeah, what I'm saying so over here like this was like literally
in the היכל. Heichal. So why does משכן Mishkan mean literally היכל
Heichal or can it be,
you know, like outside or the עזרה? Azara? Yeah, so that's an
interesting question I was wondering about too because, you know, אהל מועד
Ohel Moed means the היכל. Heichal. Why are we assuming when it
says אשר יהיה בקרקע המשכן, asher yiheiyeh be-karka ha-mishkan, it means you
go into the היכל? Heichal? Why can't you take it from the
עזרה? Azara? Yeah, that I'm not sure and I don't think that
the גמרא Gemara explains that. Okay, so let's pick up five lines
from the top on טז עמוד א. Tet-Zayin amud alef. איבעיא להו:
Ibaia lehu: so they raised the following question. אין שם עפר מהו
שיתן אפר? Ein sham afar, mahu sheyiten efer? Let's say you don't
have dust and assuming given that we or dirt actually, I should
say dirt. Given that we have said that it doesn't have to
be that you dig from the ground, at most you have to
place it on the ground. So what about something other than dirt?
What about ashes? Okay, now what's the difference? Why should ashes, I
mean, why should that be okay? It says dirt. So אליבא דבית
שמאי לא תיבעי לך. Aliba de-Beit Shammai lo tivaei lach. According to
בית שמאי Beit Shammai you have no question. דאמרי לא מצינו אפר
שקרוי עפר. De-amri lo matzinu efer she-karui afar. They say אפר efer
is never called עפר. afar. Ashes are never called dirt. כי תיבעי
לך אליבא דבית הלל. Ki tivaei lach aliba de-Beit Hillel. The question
is according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, דאמרי מצינו אפר שקרוי עפר,
de-amri matzinu efer she-karui afar,
מאי? mai? That ashes are sometimes called dirt. Where's it called dirt?
Because it says ולקח מעפר שריפת הפרה. ve-lakach me-afar sereifat ha-parah.
You shall take from literally the dust of the burning of the
פרה. parah. So this בית הלל Beit Hillel says you see that
ashes, עפר שריפת הפרה, afar sereifat ha-parah, is still called עפר. afar.
I mean obviously ואנכי עפר ואפר, Ve-anochi afar va-efer, right? Okay, but
what else would it be? So they're very similar words. Okay, but
nevertheless he says you see that ashes are called is called dust
dirt. Now בית שמאי Beit Shammai says back, "No, עפר שריפה קרוי
עפר סתם אינו קרוי." afar sereifa karui, afar stam eino karui.
It's called עפר שריפה afar sereifa is a way of saying, you
know, the dust of burning is a way of saying ashes, but
the word עפר afar by itself does not mean ashes. Now how
is this relevant? This is relevant for a הלכה halacha about, anybody
know a הלכה halacha about that you need dirt for? And can
anybody think about a הלכה halacha you need dirt for?
כיסוי הדם, Kisui ha-dam, covering the blood.
Ah no, that's yeah, but that's not biblical. Anyway, covering the blood.
כיסוי הדם. Kisui ha-dam. וכסהו בעפר. ve-kissehu be-afar. So
can you cover it with ashes? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
no, it says dirt dust and בית הלל Beit Hillel says yes,
because ashes are called עפר, afar, עפר שריפת הפרה. afar sereifat ha-parah.
So according to בית הלל Beit Hillel that by כיסוי הדם kisui
ha-dam you can cover it with ashes, how about using ashes which
is now a type of an עפר afar for him, using that
for the for סוטה? Sotah? Okay, מאי, mai, what do we say?
אף על גב דאיקרי עפר הכא בקרקע המשכן כתיב. Af al gav
de-ikarei afar, hacha be-karka ha-mishkan ktiv. Even though it's still called עפר,
afar, it still says בקרקע המשכן, be-karka ha-mishkan, which means you could
say it like you should be like if you assume you have
to lay it on the קרקע המשכן, karka ha-mishkan, then you have
to make it like קרקע המשכן. karka ha-mishkan. You don't have to
dig it from the ground, but you have to make it like
קרקע המשכן. karka ha-mishkan. רש"י Rashi just says בקרקע המשכן be-karka ha-mishkan
means, again, even if you assume you can take it out of
a basket, it has to be similar to קרקע המשכן. karka ha-mishkan.
It has to be the type of the thing that could be
of קרקע המשכן. karka ha-mishkan. So it has to be really dirt.
Or do you say that, או דילמא האי בקרקע המשכן לכדאיסי בן
יהודה ואיסי בן מנחם דאתי? o dilma hai be-karka ha-mishkan le-khid-Issi ben
Yehuda ve-Issi ben Menachem de-ati? No,
it teaches you either like איסי בן יהודה Issi ben Yehuda says
that it includes a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and נב וגבעון, Nov
ve-Givon, or what איסי בן מנחם Issi ben Menachem says that you
have to lay it on the ground. But it doesn't have to
actually be dirt. It doesn't have to be like the ground. And
if and if the word עפר afar can sometimes include אפר, efer,
ashes, maybe here too it could include ashes. Okay, so that's the
question. Let's take a look. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and here.
דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל. De-amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. בשלשה מקומות הלכה עוקבת מקרא. Be-shelosha mekomot halacha okveth mikra. In
three places
the הלכה, halacha, the tradition, undermines—that's probably a good translation of עוקבת.
okveth. Yes we do. הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. I mean
I don't—again, it's always the question whether הלכה halacha means הלכה למשה
מסיני. Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Or whatever it means, it means the tradition.
The long-standing traditional interpretation of the פסוק, pasuk, of the הלכה, halacha,
the tradition of the הלכה. halacha. רש"י Rashi says הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Undermines the verse, undermines the simple sense of the
verse. Okay. התורה אמרה, Ha-Torah amrah, the תורה Torah says בעפר, be-afar,
by the covering of the of the, you know,
כיסוי הדם, kisui ha-dam, covering the blood. והלכה בכל דבר. ve-halacha be-khol
davar. And the הלכה halacha is בכל דבר. be-khol davar. You can
cover it with anything. Now it doesn't literally mean anything. You can't
put like a book on it. But it means anything similar to
dirt in the way that רש"י Rashi says you could grow seeds
in it. Any type of a thing that is that you could,
you know, grow seeds, even if it's not dirt like apparently like,
you know, ground-up pottery or other types of things apparently is possible
for growing seeds. That would be included. It's not limited to עפר.
afar. התורה אמרה, Ha-Torah amrah, the תורה Torah says בתער. be-ta'ar. This
is by the מצורע, metzora, right? It says תער לא יעבור על
ראשו. ta'ar lo ya'avor al rosho. והלכה
בכל דבר. ve-halacha be-khol davar. And the הלכה halacha is that anyway
the hair is taken out. Remember it spoke about him combing his
hair and pulling his hair and all those types of things. The
prohibition is not limited to a razor. I'll get back to that
in a minute. התורה אמרה, Ha-Torah amrah, the
תורה Torah
says...
I said מצורע, Metzora, I meant נזיר. Nazir. I'm sorry, I said
מצורע, Metzora, I meant נזיר. Nazir.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I meant נזיר. Nazir. I'm jumping ahead because
we're going to deal with מצורע. Metzora. So עפר Afar is כיסוי
הדם, kisui hadam, תער Ta'ar is cutting the hair of a נזיר,
Nazir, okay, that the תורה HaTorah says don't cut it with a
razor and we say don't cut it with anything, and ספר sefer
write a writ of divorce, a book, a book we know what
a book looks like, and we say you could write it on
anything, you could write it on a leaf, you could write it
on the, you know, the horn of an animal, you could write
it on anything. You could write it on the arm of a
slave, so it's not the, it undermines, it undermines the simple sense
of the verse. Now, one minute, a couple things. רש"י Rashi first
of all says he doesn't like the גירסא girsa בתער beta'ar because
he says this is not undermining the verse. This is actually expanding,
being more מחמיר machmir than the verse. The תורה HaTorah says don't
do it with a razor and the הלכה halacha adds to that
don't do it with anything. It doesn't undermine, it expands. So רש"י
Rashi says well, maybe it undermines in the sense that if he
did do it with another thing, we would give him lashes and
therefore if he wasn't deserving of lashes, we would undermine the verse
of not hitting an innocent person. So it's a little okay, so
it's a little, you know, convoluted. But anyway, so רש"י Rashi prefers
a different גירסא. girsa. רש"י Rashi says this is actually the incorrect
גירסא girsa and he quotes a ספרי Sifrei I believe,
where the גירסא girsa is by the, what do you call it,
the מרצע, martzea, the awl that's used for the slave. So if
you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, oh, and
בירושלמי b'Yerushalmi exactly, five lines down in the middle-sized lines of רש"י
Rashi he says: ובמסכת קידושין ירושלמי מצאתי משנה זו רבי ישמעאל ואין
תער מן השלושה, U've'masechet Kiddushin Yerushalmi matzati mishna zu, Rabbi Yishmael, ve'ein
ta'ar min hashlosha, תער ta'ar is not mentioned,
אלא מרצע, ella martzea, the awl that's used for piercing the ear
of a slave. והכי תניא התם, V'hachi tanya hatam, התורה אמרה ספר
והלכה בכל דבר התלוש, HaTorah amra sefer ve'halacha bechol davar hatulush, anything
that is not connected to the ground.
התורה אמרה עפר והלכה בכל דבר המגדל צמחים, HaTorah amra afar ve'halacha
bechol davar hamigadel tzemachim, anything that could grow, you know,
seed. התורה אמרה מרצע והלכה אמרה אפילו סול וסירה, HaTorah amra martzea
ve'halacha amra afilu sul vesira, even some type of a thorn or,
you know, any type of a thing that will pierce, okay. והוא
נראה בעיני מאוד דהך דתער תוספת היא, Vehu nireh be'einai me'od de'hach
de'ta'ar tosefet hi, this aspect because the idea of תער ta'ar is
actually it's you're adding to the תורה, Torah, it means the interpretation
expands the תורה, Torah, doesn't undermine the תורה. Torah. So the three
places where the simple sense of the verse is you wouldn't be
יוצא yotzei if you used something other than dirt, if you used
something
other than what do you call it, an awl, if you used
something other than a book for writing a גט get and the
הלכה halacha tells you you do. Now רש"י Rashi asks a question
before we go further, why does it say that the tradition is
עוקבת, okevet, undermined? What about like all מדרשי הלכה? midrashei halacha? Exactly,
same logic.
Right. What about all מדרשי הלכה midrashei halacha that reinterpret the verse
and sometimes narrow it, sometimes they expand it, sometimes they narrow it,
you know, whatever they do, you know, so they but it changes
what we would have thought. So רש"י Rashi says because here רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, because in all the other places you have a
דרשה, drasha, so then it's not undermining, then in some way you're
saying it's embedded in the פסוקים. pesukim. There's a way we interpret
the פסוקים pesukim to come to expand it. But here רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael doesn't believe there's any דרשה. drasha. Other תנאים Tana'im have
דרשות drashot that they learn this out from, that they say that
this is actually embedded in the פסוק pasuk to include בכל דבר
bechol davar etc. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says no, I don't see
that in the פסוקים. pesukim. I know it's true by tradition, but
I don't see it in the פסוקים. pesukim. So the tradition here
for me is undermining the simple sense of the פסוקים. pesukim. I'm
not going to claim that it's a דרשה drasha embedded in the
פסוקים.
pesukim. One was about two things. Number one, that's astounding, that was
a really clear explanation. That's astounding, he had thirty-two מידות midot of
interpretation, he couldn't find one? The second thing is,
this itself is a type of hermeneutic, that עוקבת, okevet,
that's right exactly.
Then I don't know if it's a hermeneutic, it's a principle that
we can be okay with it as a matter of law that
the tradition trumps the simple sense of the פסוקים. pesukim. A hermeneutic
is a means of interpretation.
I understand but it's just anyway.
If you want to see רש"י Rashi say that, רש"י Rashi says
here two lines before the lines get wide: דרבי ישמעאל לא משמע
ליה קראי ד"וכתב לה" דמרבינא מיניה לרבות כל דבר דרשי בכסובה מגורשת
ואינה מתגורשת בכסף קידושין התם וכן כולם. de'Rabbi Yishmael lo mashme' lei
krai de'vechasav lah de'marbina minei le'rabot kol davar, darshei b'ksuva megureshet ve'einah
mitgoreshet be'khesef, kiddushin hatam, ve'chein kulam. He doesn't hold of any of
the דרשות drashot that are found in the גמרא Gemara to learn
out these הלכות halachot that we just said about other things other
than dust and other things other than a book. He doesn't have
those דרשות. drashot. אלא הלכה למשה מסיני סמכינה. Ella halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai
samchina.
The only way we know this is not based on anything we
see embedded in the פסוק, pasuk, it's pure tradition. וקראי אסמכתא בעלמא
הוא, Ve'krai asmachta be'alma hu, and any attempt to link it to
the פסוק pasuk is just an אסמכתא. asmachta. הלכך שאר מדרשים, Hilkach,
sh'ar midrashim,
all other דרשות drashot that we do, מבויין דכל התורה כולה, mibu'in
de'chol haTorah kulah, that we sort of expand you know in the
whole תורה, Torah, לא חשיב ליה רבי ישמעאל כהלכה עוקבת. lo chashiv
lei Rabbi Yishmael ke'halacha okevet. It's not undermining, it's in the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. אלא הני תלת *Ela hanei telat*, these three, he says,
are not in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* and nevertheless the traditional explanation
is going to trump the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
Basically to live with that disparity between the תורה Torah *Torah* and
the הלכה halacha. *halacha* and the פשט pshat *pshat* of the פסוקים
*psukim*.
Yeah, basically. Exactly. Now what is interesting is no, no.
Now what is interesting is
there is generally a debate even amongst like, you know, scholars today,
but it actually is a debate that is already found in the
ראשונים *rishonim*. In general, I said this before, in general about מדרש
הלכה halacha, *midrash halacha*, how much with מדרש הלכה halacha *midrash halacha*
did חזל Chazal *Chazal* start with a מסורה *masorah* or a tradition
about what the הלכה halacha *halacha* is and then they went back
and said, let's see where we can find that in the פסוקים
*psukim*, right, and that or did they start with we don't know
what the הלכה halacha *halacha* is, let's use our hermeneutics and derive
the הלכה halacha *halacha*. Now obviously sometimes it much more appears A
and sometimes it much more appears B. When there's evidence that they
started with the practice, like for example
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, how do we know פיקוח נפש
*pikuach nefesh* is דוחה שבת *docheh Shabbos*? It's clear they knew that
הלכה halacha *halacha* and then they were throwing out possible ways of
learning it from the פסוקים *psukim*. Or and especially when the דרשה
drasha *drasha* seems very, very forced. If the דרשה drasha, *drasha* seems
very, very forced, like really? You really got from that extra ו
*vav* here this whole thing? So okay, maybe you started with the
tradition and you worked back. However, when it seems that maybe the
דרשה drasha, *drasha* is not forced and it wasn't clear what the
הלכה halacha *halacha* was, then you can really assume that they're starting
with the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* and working forward. So this actually is
already debated in the ראשונים *rishonim* and it's debated by scholars and
so on. So it is interesting that רשי Rashi *Rashi* says here
we started with the הלכה halacha, *halacha*. So okay, but what I've
just told you is you could start with the הלכה halacha *halacha*
and then work backwards. But maybe what Rabbi Yishmael is saying is
maybe sometimes I start with the tradition and after you tell me
the tradition I can go back and find a way that I
can find it embedded in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Now that I
know that's the הלכה halacha *halacha*, I'm going to go back and
say, oh yes, now I see where that's where you can see
that in the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. But here he's saying I'm not
even prepared to say that even in the end. Even in the
end I'm not prepared to say I see it in the פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* and I'm just going to have to live with the
fact that that's the הלכה halacha *halacha* even though I don't see
it in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So that's why you can really
appreciate the עוקרת את המקרא *okeret et hamikra*, right? That even when
I know that I'm not going to go back and say that
that ultimately can be found through some way in the פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk*. And what's also interesting is we have many הלכות למשה מסיני
*halachos lemoshe misinai* and not every time does someone go back and
say...
yeah but most הלכות למשה מסיני *halachos lemoshe misinai* are independent of
the פסוקים *psukim*. They're not... they don't relate to the parameters of
a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*.
This is a sort of a middle sort of a phenomenon.
Exactly. Exactly. Because when you go to relate to the parameters of
a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* you don't usually talk הלכה halacha, למשה מסיני
*halacha lemoshe misinai*, you talk דרשות drashot *drashot*, you know, מדרשים *midrashim*.
Yeah.
So okay, so that's what we have. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ואי איתא *ve'i ita*, if it's true that עפר afar *afar*
of the of the סוטה sotah, *Sotah* includes ashes, so if that's
true ליחשוב נמי האי *lichshov nami hai*. So why didn't it also
mention the ashes? Now this is a very strange question for two
reasons. Number one, we already said that according to בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai* the word עפר afar. *afar* doesn't include אפר efer, *efer*. And
maybe Rabbi Yishmael holds like בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*, that's what תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* says. So why didn't you say ah well you think
that according to בית הלל Beit Hillel. *Beis Hillel* maybe it'll include
ashes by by, you know, maybe it should include it here as
well, right, it should include ashes? Yes, everybody remember that know that
question, right? So so so I don't understand. So who says we're
talking about בית הלל *Beis Hillel*? Maybe this is since Rabbi Yishmael
anyway reads the פסוקים *psukim* narrowly as has just been made evident,
maybe he fundamentally doesn't say that עפר afar *afar* includes אפר efer
*efer* even by כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam *kisuy hadam*. So how can
you say you should have added that by the case of what
you call it about the סוטה sotah? *Sotah*? The other question is
is that who says it would be עוקרת את המקרא *okeret et
hamikra*? If you're telling me the word עפר afar. *afar* means אפר
efer *efer*, then it's not עוקרת את המקרא *okeret et hamikra*, then
it's in the מקרא mikra *mikra*. So it's a very strange question.
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* really doesn't understand the question, okay. But nevertheless that's
the question. So it is like this. So it says so so
ליחשוב נמי האי *lichshov nami hai*. So if here's a place where
אפר efer *efer* is included, why isn't that in Rabbi Yishmael's list?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תנא ושייר *tana veshayer*. Oh, okay,
the list is an abbreviated list, it doesn't include everything. So the
what? Yeah, well that's what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says. What do you
mean it's an abbreviated list? It says three. Yes, but okay but
we mean as we said three but the way you would explain
it we said three, right, but you know there are more than
three, we just picked three but there are other things that exist
as well, dot dot dot. There are three we're going to give
you three but there are more things. So
maybe אפר efer *efer* is included by סוטה sota, *Sotah*, maybe other
things are also. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומאי שייר דהאי
שייר *umai shayer dehai shayer*? We don't believe that you would have
a list and you would only leave off one thing. If you
have a list that you're only leaving off one thing, put on
the one thing and have a complete list. So if you're going
to tell me things were left off the list
there must have been more than one. So what else would have
been left off the list? What else might fall under the idea
of הלכה halacha עוקרת את המקרא *halacha okeret et hamikra* that would
also be considered left off? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שייר
מצורע metzora. *shayer metzora* we left off מצורע metzora. *metzora* דתניא detanya,
*detanya* and where's מצורע metzora *metzora*? Let's take a look. והיה ביום
השביעי יגלח את כל שערו vehaya bayom hashvii yegalach et kol searo
*Vehaya bayom hashvii yegalach es kol se'aro*. Now by the מצורע *metzora*
it says when he begins his טהרה taharah *taharah* process, it says
he shaves him completely. It says יגלח את כל שערו et kol
se'aro, *yegalach es kol se'aro* and it ends
there. So day one it just says shave him without any elaboration
and day seven here’s what it says. והיה ביום השביעי יגלח את
כל שערו. כלל Klal as the general thing. את ראשו ואת זקנו
ואת גבות עיניו. Et rosho ve'et sekano ve'et gabot einav. His hair
and his beard and his eyelashes. פרט. Prat. Eyebrows. Thank you, eyebrows,
correct. That’s a narrow, that’s a specific. ואת כל שערו יגלח. Ve'et
kol se'aro yigalach. All his hair. וחזר וכלל. Vechazar vechalal. So it
goes and it’s more general, right? General, narrow, specific and general. Right.
כלל ופרט וכלל. Klal ufrat uklal. General, specific, and general. אי אתה
דן אלא כעין הפרט. Iy ata dan ela ke'ein haprat. So we
include not everything, but we don’t say only the things that are
specific, but anything similar to what is specific. What is that? מה
הפרט מפורש מקום כינוס שיער ונראה. Ma haprat meforash mekom kinus se'ar
venireh. The same way the פרט prat is explicit, that it is
a place where hair gathers, right? It’s not just random strands of
hair, there’s like a collection of hair, you know, your eyebrows, your
hair, your beard. So and is visible. אף כל מקום כינוס שיער
ונראה. Af kol mekom kinus se'ar venireh. Any place that hair is
gathered and visible. So what exists here other than what we’ve mentioned?
מה ריבה? Ma ribah? What’s included that hasn’t been mentioned? רבי אומר
שיער הרגליים. Rabbi omer se'ar haraglayim. The hair of the legs, which
means the pubic hair. Okay, so that that’s נראה nireh because it
doesn’t mean נראה nireh when you’re wearing clothes, but נראה nireh when
you’re standing naked. Okay, so that’s a place where there’s hair is
gathered, so that would be included.
And why shouldn’t it be נראה nireh when you’re naked?
I don’t know. That’s how I understand it. You know, you can
always decide, you know, I mean it’s always up to, why didn’t
it say מה הפרט מפורש שיער שבראש? Ma haprat meforash se'ar shebarosh?
You know? So it’s always up to חז"ל Chazal to understand what
are they seeing as the defining characteristics, you know? When you have
to say similar to the specifics, it’s up to חז"ל to determine
what are the significant characteristics that they’re going to say, you know,
is the common denominator of these things. Or hair in the underarms?
Alright, well that’s what we’re going to exclude. Okay, so it has
to it means visible, but visible when you’re naked. So it would
include the pubic hair. מה מיעט? Ma mi'et? What would it exclude?
מיעט בית השחי. Mi'et beit hashachi. It would exclude the underarm hair
because if you’re standing normally you’d have to lift up your arms,
right? So even if you’re standing naked, it’s not. ודכולי גופא. Vedechulei
gufa. And of course other places on the body where it’s just
individual strands of hair and not a whole collection of hair. Okay,
so that’s the so basically what you have here is the
פסוק pasuk. is quite interesting.
This isn't he didn't complete his arms, right?
Or was it? No, not on יום השביעי. yom hashvi'i. On יום
השביעי yom hashvi'i you only say shave the
hair bunches of hair. The head of the hair, the beard, the
eyebrows, and the pubic hair. The rest of the body you don’t
shave. That would be the פשט הפסוק. pshat hapasuk. That’s not the
הלכה. halacha That’s the פשט of the פסוק. pasuk. כלל ופרט וכלל
Klal ufrat uklal is the פשט הפסוק. pshat hapasuk. So the פשט
of the פסוק pasuk? is only those areas and but comes along
the הלכה, halacha, okay? והלכתא. Vehilchata. I’m
sorry. מה מיעט? Ma mi'et? והלכתא, Vehilchata, but the הלכה halacha comes
and teaches you מגלח כדלעת. megaleach kedala'at. You shave him like a
gourd. Okay, so you shave off all his hair. So you do
that on day one and you do that again on day seven
even though the פשט הפסוק pshat hapasuk would not have you shave
him fully on day seven, הלכה עוקבת את המקרא. halacha okevet et
hamikra. Okay, so he says ah, here’s another example of הלכה עוקבת
את המקרא. halacha okevet et hamikra. So therefore, is it a left
off the list? It’s not a קשיא, kashya, it’s an answer. The
question is why if ashes work for סוטה, Sotah? why isn’t it
on this list? Okay, although for I don’t know why that’s considered
to be עוקבת, okevet, but whatever it is, why isn’t it on
this list as ashes work for סוטה? Sotah And the answer is
it’s an incomplete list. How is it incomplete? What else is left
off? This is left off. Here’s a place where the הלכה halacha.
undermines because the הלכה would only be the places of bunches of
hair and the הלכה is all of the hair.
And the answer is why they pick these two and not those
two?
I don’t know. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, דתנן בא לו
להקיף את המצורע. detnan ba lo lehakif et hametzora. That’s Rashi. You
come to cut off the hair of the מצורע. מעביר תער על
כל בשרו. Ma'avir ta'ar al kol besaro. All his hair. That’s on
day one. וקתני סיפא, Uktani seifa, and it says at the end,
וביום השביעי מגלחו תגלחת שנייה. Uvayom hashvi'i megalecho tiglachat shniya. You do
a second shaving. כתגלחת ראשונה, Ketiglachat rishona, like the first one meaning
and also, you know, as a cucumber, bald as a cucumber. Okay,
so it’s the same thing, right? It’s a gourd or whatever. Okay,
so so you see so that’s another thing that was left off.
So now we can say that’s why ashes was left off because
other things are left off as well. So the גמרא Gemara. says
no no no, that’s not exclude, that’s not a leaving off of
the list, that doesn’t belong on the list in the first place.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. כי קא
חשיב הלכה עוקבת מקרא. Ki ka chashiv halacha okevet mikra. We’re talking
about when the הלכה overrides the simple sense of the verse. הא
עוקבת מדרבנן היא. Ha okevet midirabanan hi. This, I think what this
means, I’m curious what Artscroll says, Rashi explains, but I think what
this means is it’s not undermining the פשט of the פסוק, pasuk
it’s undermining the דרש drash of the פסוק. pasuk. So it’s not
the same thing of עוקבת את
המקרא. okevet et hamikra. It’s עוקבת את הדרש של המקרא. okevet et
hadrash shel hamikra. Right, because the מקרא Mikra, says את כל שערו,
so it’s not clear in the פסוק pasuk it doesn’t mean all
of the hair. The דרש drash tells you it only means the
bunches of hair. So that what does the Artscroll say? It says
that basically what they’re saying? Okay fine.
Undermines rabbinic explanation. Yeah fine.
It’s but it is funny that it calls it מדרבנן. midirabanan. Okay
but anyway. One minute. So therefore it’s not עוקבת okevet the מקרא,
Mikra. it’s עוקבת okevet the דרשה of the מקרא. רב פפא Rav
Pappa אמר amar כי חשיב הלכה עוקבת ועוקרת. ki chashiv halacha okavet
ve’okaret. No, no, no. Here’s another reason why this doesn’t belong on
the list, because we talk about when the הלכה comes and we
said undermines. So if you were to follow the new הלכה, you
wouldn’t have been יוצא yotze the way the פסוק pasuk. described it.
Right? If you write a גט get on a leaf, you’re not
יוצא yotze writing it on a ספר. sefer. You wouldn’t be יוצא
yotze the simple sense of the
פסוק. pasuk If you cover the blood with ground up shards, no,
that won’t work, ground up pottery, you wouldn’t be יוצא yotze the
simple sense of the פסוק pasuk of dust. But here, if you
shave the entire guy, you’re also fulfilling the פסוק. pasuk, You’re just
doing more. Okay? This isn’t we’re talking about עוקבת ועוקרת okevet ve'okaret
undermines.
הא ha עוקבת ומוספת היא. okevet umosefet hi. This is going around,
but it’s actually adding, it’s not undermining. Okay. Now that’s answer number
two why it’s not on the list. Here’s answer number three why
it’s not on the list. רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר amar הא
מתניתא מני? ha matnita mani? רבי ישמעאל היא. Rabbi Yishmael hi. One
minute. This ברייתא braita about three things that are עוקבת, okevet, that’s
a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael position. דדרש כלל ופרט. dedarash klal ufrat.
So he does a כלל ופרט. klal ufrat. So and
that according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the simple sense of the
פסוק, pasuk you’re right,
would be limited to the bunches of hair and the pubic hair
etcetera and would not be the whole body. And you know what?
That actually is what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say would be
the הלכה of the מצורע. That on day seven you would only
do the bunches of hair. So what’s the teaching that you do
the whole body? That’s not רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. That’s רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. So תדלא מהני? tedala mehani? Who’s the opinion that says
you shave him like a
cucumber? That’s רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva here. That’s רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
דדרש ריבוי ומיעוט. dedarash ribbuy umiut. He does the ריבוי ומיעוט. ribbuy
umiut. You might remember this. We had some fun גמרות gemarot like
this in נזיר. Nazir. The basic difference is the following. כלל ופרט
וכלל klal ufrat ukhlal says that when you have general, specific, and
general, the הלכה is anything similar to the specific.
Okay. ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי ribbuy miut uribbuy says no. Once you have
the general and the specific, if you just were to stop there,
it would already be anything similar to the specific. So when you
then add the third thing, the ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי, ribbuy miut uribbuy,
now you basically include everything under the sun with the exception of
the things that are the most different, that are completely unrelated, that
are the complete opposite of what is being described.
Right. Okay. So the one that says a cucumber, that’s רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva דדרש ריבוי ומיעוט. dedarash ribbuy umiut. דתניא, we taught in
a ברייתא. braita. We have to move a place. This is just
way too disruptive today. והיה ביום השביעי יגלח את כל שערו ריבה,
riba, all the hair. That’s including. את ראשו ואת זקנו ואת גבות
עיניו et rosho ve'et sekano ve'et givot einav מיעט. miat. That is
limiting. ואת כל שערו יגלח ve'et kol searo yegalach חזר וריבה. chazar
veriba. That’s once again being including. Okay. ריבה ומיעט וריבה, riba umiat
veriba, inclusive, limiting, and inclusive or expanding. ריבה הכל. riba hakol. So
מה ריבה? ma riba? Everything is included. ריבה דכוליה גופיה, riba dechulei
gufeih, all the body. So once you have a ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי,
ribbuy miut uribbuy, you’re basically including everything under the sun. The only
thing you exclude is something that is most different. ומה מיעט? uma
miat? What do you exclude? מיעט שיער שבתוך החוטם. miat sear shebetoch
hachotem. Ah, the one thing you don’t have to do is the
nose hair. Okay, but you weren’t even thinking about that. I would
say what could you exclude if you did the whole body? What
are you not doing? You’re not doing the nose hair. Maybe the
ear hair also. Okay. So basically it’s saying you said רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael should have included this as an example where the הלכה
is עוקבת. okevet. This isn’t an issue of הלכה עוקבת. halacha okavet.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say you only do the bunches of
hair. And the position that says you do him like a cucumber
isn’t because of the הלכה, it’s because of a רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva position of reading the פסוק pasuk, in a different way that
would basically say ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribbuy umiut veribbuy you do everything
except the nose hair. So it’s basically just two different דרשות of
the פסוק. pasuk It’s not a case of הלכה עוקבת. halacha okavet.
So we have three reasons why shaving him like a cucumber isn’t
included. One is it only undermines the דרשה, not the simple sense
of the פסוק. pasuk One is because it adds to the פסוק,
pasuk? it doesn’t undermine the פסוק. pasuk, And the third is because
actually it’s not הלכה against the דרשה, it’s a רבי ישמעאל דרשה
Rabbi Yishmael drasha against a רבי עקיבא דרשה. Rabbi Akiva drasha. So
there are three ways why this isn’t isn’t excluded. So we’re sort
of back to our first question, which is, well, why isn’t ashes
on the list? If you could use ashes for a סוטה, Sotah.
isn’t that an example of עוקבת? okevet? Although as תוספות said, it’s
not really עוקבת okevet because maybe if עפר afar means אפר, efer
that’s what I’m saying,
but maybe that’s not a case of עוקבת. okevet. But anyway, so
it’s not so clear. We don’t have a good explanation why it’s
on the list. We haven’t really resolved our question about the ashes.
So let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. So מה הוי עלה?
ma hava alah? What was the upshot? תא שמע. ta shema. Come
and hear. דאמר רב הונא בר אשי אמר רב, de'amar Rav Huna
bar Ashi amar Rav, אין שם עפר, ein sham afar, if there’s
no dirt,
מביא רקבובית ירק. mevi rakvuvit yarak. You can bring the sort of
the rotting of
the what’s it called? The dust of a vegetable, the vegetable, the
decomposed vegetable.
Now ומקדש umekadesh and you can use that to sanctify the water.
Now is that the same as ashes? I mean that is somewhat
similar to ground at least, it’s something that grew from the ground
and it’s not exactly the same as ashes, it underwent a whole
different change of process. Anyway so that’s what the גמרא Gemara says.
ולא היא velo hi actually that’s not a good comparison. רקבובית ירק
הוא דהוה עפר. rikvuvit yerek hu de-havei afar. That could be considered
dirt. אפר לא הוה עפר. efer lo havei afar. Ashes not. It
doesn’t exactly explain what the difference is but you know, again, ashes
are burnt and so on, this is actually just natural decomposed and
it’s something that grew from the ground. So at the end of
the day we do expand dirt to some degree, but it’s a
question whether we would expand it all the way to include even
ashes. Yes.
Yeah the reason why I asked context confused a minute ago because
that’s the קשיא kashya and there’s already the תירוץ teretz is because
כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam, is the first one on the list. Right,
right. So the minute they established that for כיסוי הדם, kisuy hadam
אפר efer can serve as עפר. afar Right, right. Why isn’t the
גמרא Gemara simply say once you’ve got a
like something synonymous between those two terms?
Well that was the גמרא’s Gemara question, can we learn out from
כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam to apply it to סוטה? Sotah. That was
the sense of the גמרא.
Gemara But it’s interesting that they in I understand they frame the
question that way.
You mean why did they give an answer that כיסוי הדם kisuy
hadam is meant to include the סוטה Sotah case?
No they frame it from כיסוי הדם to סוטה. Sotah. Yeah why
but but you could frame it like once the word has that
meaning then the word can be
That’s exactly what the גמרא Gemara. says. In one area of הלכה
we know the word means this. But the גמרא Gemara actually that’s
exactly the גמרא’s Gemara question. Should we say it always means it?
Maybe it would but here since the תורה emphasizes בקרקע המשכן, be-karka
ha-mishkan,
maybe it’s סתם עפר stam afar maybe includes אפר efer? for בית
הלל. But when it’s called עפר בקרקע המשכן, afar be-karka ha-mishkan, maybe
it has to be more like dirt. Okay? Maybe this context shows
you maybe under normal situation עפר afar, would include אפר efer but
this particularly associates it with קרקע משכן. karka mishkan. That was exactly
the גמרא’s question. Yeah but there’s something specific about this context. Yeah.
So then he’d be asking why אפר efer. is not on the
list, right?
Why why אפר efer? is not on the list? אפר for סוטה.
Sotah והעפר ve-ha'afar that’s associated with קרקע karka would that be expanded
to include אפר? That’s the question. And in the end the גמרא
says maybe not, maybe even if we expand it a little bit
like the decomposed vegetables we wouldn’t expand it for this. Yes.
רב הונא בר אשי Rav Huna bar Ashi would be the last
generation of אמוראים. Amoraim.
Okay I’ll take your word for that.
I mean רב אשי Rav Ashi was
the Oh okay if it’s the same רב אשי. Rav Ashi. Right,
right, right, right.
And then the next line sort of contradicts him, so that might
have been
Well clearly the סתם stam is assumed to come after the named
אמוראים. Amoraim. Yeah, I mean it’s true רש״י Rashi often assumes like
the סתם stam is רבינא ורב אשי. Ravina ve-Rav Ashi. That's a
good point. But you know the the obvious problem on that is
that there are later right positions than רבינא ורב אשי. Ravina ve-Rav
Ashi. Yes so there's another good that’s a good point evidence to
this. Certainly today it’s like taken for granted that the סתם stam
I mean maybe not all סתם stam everywhere but you know סתם
stam is mostly post you know later than the named אמוראים. Amoraim.
Okay. כדי שייראה על המים kedei she-yera'eh al ha-mayim so you put
the dirt in and then it appears on the water. Okay so
it doesn’t like just sink to the bottom or guess or maybe
it’s exactly the question whether that means that it floats to the
top, you know, or does it like muddy the water? It sounds
like from an earlier רש״י Rashi that it means על המים al
ha-mayim not במים ba-mayim that like it somehow some of the dirt
like is floating on the top.
תנו רבנן tanu rabanan so our Rabbis taught. שלשה צריכים שייראו. shelosha
tzerichim she-yeira'u. Three things have to be seen. עפר סוטה afar Sotah
the the dirt of a סוטה Sotah when it’s put in the
water, ואפר פרה ve-efer parah the ashes of the פרה parah when
that’s put in the water, ורוק יבמה ve-rok yevamah and the spit
of a יבמה. yevamah. It says וירקה בפניו ve-yarkah be-fanav right? She
spits in his presence לעיני הזקנים le-einei ha-zekenim to the eyes of
the זקנים zekenim which means they have to be able to see
the spit. Okay. משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו mishum Rabbi Yishmael amru in
the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael they said אף דם ציפור
af dam tzippor even the blood of the bird for the whole
טהרה process of the מצורע where it says that you slaughter one
of the birds and the blood goes into the water it has
to be visible. So we'll see what all this means. מאי טעמא
דרבי ישמעאל mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yishmael what’s the reason of רבי ישמעאל?
Rabbi Yishmael? דכתיב de-chtiv as it is written וטבל אותם בדם הציפור
השחוטה ובמים החיים ve-taval otam be-dam ha-tzippor ha-shechutah u-va-mayim ha-chayim I think
is the פסוק. pasuk? Right, he shall dip them, the עץ ארז
etz erez and the אזוב ezov and the שני תולעת shani tola'at
in the blood of the slaughtered of the slaughtered bird and in
the water. Okay. ותניא ve-tanya בדם be-dam in the blood יכול בדם
בלא מים yachol be-dam belo mayim maybe you only dip it in
the
blood? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar במים. ba-mayim. What’s the פסוק? pasuk, The
actual פסוק pasuk, is, let's read the
פסוק. pasuk, ושחטו את הציפור
האחת אל כלי חרס על מים חיים.
ve-shachatu et
ha-tzippor
ha-achat
el keli cheres al mayim chayim. So it’s על מים חיים al
mayim chayim and then... It says וטבל אותם ואת הצפור החיה בדם
הצפור השחטה על המים החיים. V'taval otam v'et hatzippor hachayah b'dam hatzippor
hashchutah al hamayim hachayim. Okay, so it's in the blood on the
water. Okay, so תלמוד לומר. Talmud lomar. In the water, living water.
על מים. Al mayim. אי מים, I mayim, if you dip it
in the water, not just the blood, and so it's not just
the blood, it says water. יכול במים ולא בדם, Yachol b'mayim v'lo
b'dam, just do it in the water. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, בדם.
b'dam. No, dip it in the blood. So what are you dipping
it in? The water or the blood? הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? מביא
מים שדם צפור ניכר בהם. Mevi mayim she'dam tzippor nikar bahem. You
bring waters that is not so much. Waters that even after you
shecht the bird, the blood will still be visible. I'll discuss in
a minute what visible means. I mean a little blood, you'll certainly—the
water will turn red. But we'll see that the blood is still
visible. וכמה, V'kamah, and how much water would not overwhelm the blood?
רביעית. Revi'is. רביעית. Revi'is. So therefore it has to basically appear like
blood. So yes, it's the blood and the water mixed together. It's
not just the blood, but it's a limited amount of water so
that the blood is still visible. Now Tosafot discusses, you know, why
only
a revi'is? I mean, even a drop of blood will be—will change
the appearance of the water. So Tosafot says yes, but here the
point is not that the water is—I mean, the language is here,
I think, נראה בהם, ner'eh bahem, not ניכר בהם, nikar bahem, right?
No, it is actually, it's ניכר, nikar, it is ניכר. nikar. It's
not נראה. ner'eh. But anyway, but Tosafot says the position is not
that you can understand—know that blood was there. It has to be
that it basically is still considered the blood. Like is it watered-down
blood, or is it blood with a—is it water with a little
bit of blood? You understand what—right? I mean, how do we relate
to it? To relate to it as like blood that's had—that's had
a little bit of water mixed to it, but basically I say
what I've got here is I've got blood. All right, watered-down blood,
but I've got blood, I've got the ממשות mamashus of blood. Or
do we say, no, I've got water that has been impurified that
has had some blood added to it? Okay, that, you know, that
has—so is it basically water with the presence of blood or is
it blood with the presence of water is a way of saying
it. So the way Tosafot says is you need the ממשות mamashus
of blood. So you need water's got to be there, but it
can't be so much. It has to still basically be able to
say וטבל אותם בדם הצפור v'taval otam b'dam hatzippor that you're still
dipping it into the blood and therefore the amount of water has
to be limited. So when Rabbi Yishmael says here that the דם
dam has to be ניכר, nikar, he means more than just ניכר
nikar is like you can sense that there is blood there present.
He means it really has to be like the ממשות mamashus of
blood. That's how Tosafot understands it. Yes, Jenna?
Does—so the רביעית revi'is is how much blood there is?
No, how much water. Water, only three ounces of water. It can't—it
has to be a limited amount of water because if it's too
much water, right, it'll then it'll—it'll—like it'll—not diffuse is the word—like—anyway, yeah,
it'll—it'll, you know, it'll—it'll diffuse the blood too much. Okay, so that's
his position. It has to be ניכר, nikar, but again, Tosafot says
ניכר nikar means not just that you can sense that there's blood
present, but it has to really be like the ממשות mamashus of
blood.
Okay, get—similar question to what you said?
Well, yeah, that's a—similar the point—that it can't be like it's—yeah, yes,
I mean it's similar to ביטול bittul issues. To what degree is
the thing not there and its—and only its appearance is left or
its taste is left or something, or to what degree is fundamentally
the original thing still there? And that's exactly what Tosafot is saying.
It has to be a limited amount of water, only three ounces,
so you could say the blood is still present. Okay, that's Rabbi
Yishmael's position. רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis who did not have this on
their list, presumably they do not require such a limited amount of
water. ההוא לגופיה. Hahu legufei. That's—no, the emphasis of blood and water
is not to tell you the blood has to be physically present
like so much that it's like still there, but it's to tell
you for the just simple sense of the פסוק pasuk that you
have to mix the blood and the water together. דהכי קאמר רחמנא,
D'hachi ka'amar Rachmana, טבול בדם ובמים. t'vol b'dam u'v'mayim. Dip it in
a mixture of blood and water. So it doesn't have to say—it
doesn't have to be בדם. b'dam. I mean, you understand, by the
way, Rabbi Yishmael is a good reader of the פסוק. pasuk It
says וטבל אותם בדם הצפור השחטה על המים החיים. V'taval otam b'dam
hatzippor hashchutah al hamayim hachayim. It seems like fundamentally you're still treating
it as blood, not as a mixture. Okay, but the חכמים Chachamim
say no, it doesn't have to be that much—that much blood or
it doesn't have to be that little water. דם ומים Dam u'mayim
just means a mixture. Rabbi Yishmael, אם כן, im kein, if all
it was saying was a mixture, ליכתוב רחמנא וטבל בהם. lichtov Rachmana
v'taval bahem. Just say in them. בדם ובמים למה לי? B'dam u'v'mayim
lama li? לניכר. L'nikar. The reason it starts—it identifies them separately and
starts with saying דם dam is that the דם dam has to
be very present. ורבנן, V'rabbanan, the Rabbis would say, אי כתב רחמנא
וטבל בהם, ei ketav Rachmana v'taval bahem, in them,
הוה אמינא האי לחודיה והאי לחודיה. hava amina hai lachudei v'hai lachudei.
I would have said first dip in blood and then dip in
water. Maybe it would mean them singly, not combined. קא משמע לן
רחמנא בדם ובמים Ka mashma lan Rachmana b'dam u'v'mayim לעורבן l'arvan to
tell you that they have to be mixed together. I don't know,
if you ask me, בדם ומים b'dam u'mayim more means separate than
together. I don't know what to tell you. ורבי ישמעאל לעורבן מקרא
אחרינא נפקא. V'Rabbi Yishmael l'arvan mikra achrina nafka. No, you know from
another פסוק they're already mixed. How do you know from another פסוק
they're mixed? It says ושחט את הצפור האחת אל כלי חרס על
מים חיים V'shachat et hatzippor ha'achat el kli cheres al mayim chayim
that you shecht the צפור tzippor on a vessel over water. So
if you're shechting it over water... water, of course you're mixing it.
So there's a great גמרא. רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבי Rebbe will tell
you no, I got a way you can שחט shecht the bird
over water and it won't get mixed. How are you going to
do it? אי מהא, Ei meha, if it was just that, הוה
אמינא hava amina I would say, לשחטיה סמוך למנא, lishchatei samuch lemana,
שחט shecht the bird near the vessel, ונינקטינהו לורידין, veninktinhu leveridin,
and sort of grab onto, put pressure on the, you know, on
the
arteries, and וליקבליה לדמיה במנא אחרינא, velikbelei ledamei bemana achrina, and hold
it down and keep the blood from squirting out, and then וליקבליה
לדמיה במנא אחרינא, velikbelei ledamei bemana achrina, and then have it released
in another vessel. I'm sorry, no. Just because it says שחט shecht
it over another vessel does not mean you must mix them. Okay?
It means that your instinct is to think it means to do
that and then
no, it's not that that's your instinct. It's just saying,
if it was just for the פסוק, I wouldn't have been able
to rule out the following scenario. Oh look, technically I did what
the פסוק says, I שחט shechted it over the vessel with the
water, and then I just released it in another vessel. Okay, so
you wouldn't have been able to rule that out. We're not saying
that's פשט of the פסוק, but you wouldn't have been able to
rule it out. So you needed a פסוק to tell you to
mix it. Okay. קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. Okay.
פשיטא, Pshita, no one over eight years old would read the פסוק
that way.
Fine. All right. Anyway, anyway so that's why he says that by
the blood, but the rabbis disagree. And again the way תוספות explains
it, the question is a little bit of blood far obviously will
go a long way to color the water, but we need there
to be according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael so much that it
really feels like the ממשות mamashus of the blood is there. So
בעי מיניה רב ירמיה מרבי זירא, Ba'ei minei Rav Yirmiya meRabbi Zeira,
רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya asked רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. רב ירמיה Rav
Yirmiya tends to be a little bit of a troublemaker about trying
to like ask so let's see what he says.
גדולה ומדחת את המים, Gedola umadachat et hamayim, let's say you've got
a big bird. Okay? And it's so much that it will completely
overwhelm the water. So it won't, you'll be able like it won't
get a sense that there's any water present. Okay? Because it still
has to be blood plus water. Let's say it's so much blood
that there won't even be a sense that there was any water
there. Or קטנה ונמחית מפני המים, ktana venimchit mipnei hamayim, let's say
it's a very small bird so it's overwhelmed by the water. How
can you always say a רביעית? revi'is? So מהו, mahu, what's the
law? So תוספות says the question really isn't like he's asking what's
the הלכה, he's really challenging the position. How can you always say
a רביעית? revi'is? Who decrees that it's always a רביעית? revi'is? If
it's a bigger bird you'll need more water, and if it's a
smaller bird you'll need less water. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira said to
him, לאו אמינא לך לא תפיק נפשך לבר מהלכתא, lav amina lach
lo teippek nafshach levar mehilchata, haven't I told you don't make trouble?
That's the loose translation. Haven't I told you like don't try to
find a way to sort of, you know, outdo like, you know,
challenge the הלכה in this way, outsmart the
הלכה. בציפור דרור, Betzippor dror, שיערו רבנן. shi'eru Rabbanan. The rabbis when
they said a רביעית revi'is were talking about a particular type of
bird, a ציפור דרור, tzippor dror, which is I don't know how
they translate that, a sparrow. אין לך גדולה שמדחת את המים, Ein
lach gedola shemadachat et hamayim, and when you're dealing with sparrows,
you don't have really big sparrows. You don't have any sparrow big
enough that it'll be a problem with a רביעית revi'is of water.
ואין לך קטנה שנמחית מפני המים, Ve'ein lach ktana shenimchit mipnei hamayim,
and you don't have any really small sparrows that the water will
overwhelm. Within the range of sparrows, a רביעית revi'is does just fine.
Okay. So don't be such a wise guy. We're dealing with sparrows
and a רביעית revi'is is a good שיעור shiur for the whole
range of sparrows. Okay. Now, so that was that. Now we get
back to this issue about let's get back to the סוטה. Sotah
And you put the ashes of the סוטה Sotah, in the water
and the ashes have to appear on the water. Okay? So now
we're going to discuss exactly something of the sequence. Let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הקדים עפר למים Hikdim afar lemayim פסול.
pasul. If you put the ashes, the dirt, excuse me, not the
ashes, the dirt of and then the water, first you did the
dirt and then the water, it's invalid. Because it says that you
shall take from the dirt ונתן אל המים, venatan el hamayim, put
it into the water. So the water has to be in the
vessel first. Okay. רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rabbi Shimon machshir. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says no, even if you reverse it you're okay. מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון, Mai ta'ama deRabbi Shimon, what's the reasoning?
דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says ולקחו לטמא מעפר שרפת החטאת. velakchu latamei
mei'afar sreifat hachatat. Because it says by the פרה אדומה, parah adumah,
here again we're going to compare פרה אדומה parah adumah אפר to
the עפר. afar.
We did it on the, and here it also the ashes have
to appear on the water, the dirt has to appear on the
water. So what does it say by the פרה אדומה? parah adumah?
It says ולקחו לטמא מעפר שרפת החטאת. velakchu latamei mei'afar sreifat hachatat.
You shall take for the impure person from the burn- the dirt
of the burning of the חטאת. chatat. So use the word עפר
when it's referring here to
אפר. ותניא, Vetanya, אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, וכי עפר הוא?
vechi afar hu? Is the thing by the פרה אדומה parah adumah
dirt? והלא אפר הוא? vehalo efer hu? It's ashes. ששינה הכתוב במשמעו,
Sheshina hakatuv bemashma'o, so why did it say עפר when it really
should be saying אפר? So it changes from the simple meaning לדון
הימנו גזירה שוה, ladun heimenu gezeirah shavah, that we should learn from
it a way of connecting it. נאמר כאן עפר, Ne'emar kan afar,
it says by פרה אדומה parah adumah עפר, ונאמר להלן עפר, v'ne'emar
lehalan afar, and it says by the סוטה Sotah עפר. מה להלן
עפר על גבי מים, Ma lehalan afar al gabei mayim, the same
way by the סוטה Sotah, it's dirt
has to be on
top of water... somewhere that's understood that the dirt is seen on
the top of the water, so that's what we know about the
סוטה, Sotah. אף כאן עפר גבי מים, Af kan afar gabei mayim,
here too by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, when you put the
ashes in the water, the ashes have to be seen on the
top of the water. So that's what we learn out, that's where
סוטה Sotah, teaches you something about פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. And then
we also do it in the reverse. ומאן כאן, U'man kan, what
do we know by the ashes of the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah?
הקדים עפר למים כשר, Hikdim afar le'mayim kasher, that if you put
the ashes in first it's כשר. kasher. We're going to know in
a minute where we know that from. אף להלן הקדים עפר למים
כשר, Af le'halan hikdim afar le'mayim kasher, so even by the סוטה,
Sotah if you put the dirt in first it's כשר. kasher. So
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we link the two. On the one
hand we learn out that by the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah the
ashes have to be visible, but on the other hand we learn
out in the other direction that you can reverse the order, that
the dirt can go first. So how do we know that by
the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? So the גמרא says והתם מנלן, V'hatam
minalan, where do you know that by the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah?
תרי קראי כתיבי, Trei kraei ktivi, there are two verses. כתיב עליו,
Ktiv alav, it says ונתן עליו, v'natan alav,
what's the פסוק? רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, hold on,
where's the פסוק? רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, hold on. ונתן עליו
מים חיים אל כלי. V'natan alav mayim chayim el keli. Okay, exactly.
So actually you put the water on the ashes. It says ונתן
עליו מים חיים אל כלי. v'natan alav mayim chayim el keli. That's
the פסוק, ולקחו לטמא מעפר שרפת החטאת, v'lakchu la'tamei me'afar s'reifat ha'chatat,
you take from the burning of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, ונתן
עליו, v'natan alav, you put on the ashes מים חיים אל כלי.
mayim chayim el keli. Okay, so that sounds like the ashes are
first. Okay, so there it says כתיב עליו. ktiv alav. אלמא אפר
ברישא, Alma efer b'reisha, the ashes are first, the exact opposite of
the סוטה. Sotah וכתיב מים חיים אל כלי, u'chtiv mayim chayim el
keli, but it also says living water to the vessel. אלמא מים
ברישא. Alma mayim b'reisha. Now how do you get that? Like the
simple sense of the verse is ונתן עליו, v'natan alav, put on
the ashes מים חיים, mayim chayim, living water אל כלי, el keli,
they should be poured into the vessel. But the דרש is no,
מים חיים אל כלי, mayim chayim el keli, the water starts in
the vessel. The מים חיים mayim chayim is in the כלי keli
and the ashes go on it. So one thing says the water
is put on the ashes, and the other says the water is
the first thing that starts in the vessel. So אלמא מים ברישא.
alma mayim b'reisha. הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? How do you reconcile it?
רצה זה נותן רצה זה נותן. Ratza zeh noten ratza zeh noten.
So you can do it either way. Okay, so by the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah we learn from עליו alav and אל כלי el
keli it can be either way. So by the סוטה, Sotah, presumably
by the סוטה Sotah, we don't say it's completely equivalent, לכתחלה l'chatchila
you're supposed to put the dirt in the water, that's the simple
sense of the פסוק, right?
אשר
יהיה בקרקע המשכן ונתן אל המים, Asher yihiyeh b'karka hamishkan v'natan el
hamayim, you put it in the water, the water is there first.
But we learn from פרה אדומה Parah Adumah that בדיעבד b'diavad if
you reverse it it's also good. Okay, so רצה זה נותן ורצה
זה נותן. ratza zeh noten v'ratza zeh noten. ורבנן, V'rabbanan, and the
Rabbis not only do they disagree by סוטה Sotah but they also
disagree by the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. אל כלי El keli is
not to tell you that that is דווקא. davka. This is interesting,
talk about מקרא או הלכה עוקבת את המקרא, mikra o halacha okevet
et hamikra, they actually say no, that in both of them it's
the same. The water has to be first. The water has to
be first by סוטה, Sotah and the water has to be first
by פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, even though the simple sense of the
פסוק is ונתן עליו מים חיים. v'natan alav mayim chayim. No, we're
saying מים חיים אל כלי, mayim chayim el keli, the water has
to start first in the vessel. That's required. עליו? Alav? So what
does it mean עליו? alav? לערבן, L'arvan, it means after you add
the ashes, you stir it up. So the מים חיים mayim chayim
starts אל כלי, el keli, you put the ashes in and then
ונתן עליו v'natan alav is then you turn the water over on
top of it and you mix it up. You fold it together.
ואימא עליו דווקא? V'eima alav davka? Why not say the opposite? עליו
Alav is דווקא, davka, the ashes start, and אל כלי el keli
means what does אל כלי el keli tell you? Not it starts
in the vessel, but שתהא חיותן בכלי, she'tehei chiyutan b'keli, they have
to draw the water straight with the vessel you're going to use.
You don't draw it with another vessel, you draw it with the
vessel that you're using. ממה נפשך? Mimah nafshach? No. So the גמרא
says no, we don't say that. ממה מצינו בכל מקום מכשיר למעלה.
Mimah matzinu b'chol makom machshir l'mala. We always find that the relevant
material, the potent material if you would, the מכשיר, machshir, the thing
that's making it good goes on top. The water is just the
solution, it's the thing you add to the
solution that is the thing that goes on top. אף כאן מכשיר
למעלה. Af kan machshir l'mala. So where else do we find it?
Well, סוטה, the simple sense of the סוטה is you start with
the water. Okay, so therefore here too, and רש"י has also the
blood of the bird. Remember the blood of the bird that you
slaughtered into the water? So by סוטה and by the bird you
always start with the water and you add the dirt.
On top the מכשיר machshir is really the second thing that goes
in.
Yeah, but it's the potent thing, it's the non-water, it's the thing
being added to the water that's special, that's special. So you always
start with the water and you add this. So for the Rabbis
the... It's not the simple sense of the פסוק by פרה אדומה,
Parah Adumah, but in both cases you start with the water and
you add the thing second and that's מעכב. meakev. And according to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you could actually go in either way, either
direction in both cases. Okay. Okay.